<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles ecclesiasticall to be inquired of by the churchwardens and the sworne-men within the dioces of Hereforde in the visitation of the reuerend father in God, Harbart Bishop of the saide dioces, this present yeare M.D.LXXXXII. and in the XXXIIII. yeare of the raigne of our most gratious soueraigne lady Queene Elizabeth, &amp;c. and so hereafter till the next visitation, &amp; from time to time to bee presented.</title>
            <author>Church of England. Diocese of Hereford. Bishop (1586-1602 : Westfaling)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1592</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00185</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10215.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4281</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24048339</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24048339</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27118</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00185)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27118)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1815:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles ecclesiasticall to be inquired of by the churchwardens and the sworne-men within the dioces of Hereforde in the visitation of the reuerend father in God, Harbart Bishop of the saide dioces, this present yeare M.D.LXXXXII. and in the XXXIIII. yeare of the raigne of our most gratious soueraigne lady Queene Elizabeth, &amp;c. and so hereafter till the next visitation, &amp; from time to time to bee presented.</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Diocese of Hereford. Bishop (1586-1602 : Westfaling)</author>
                  <author>Westfaling, Herbert, 1532?-1602.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ioseph Barnes, printer to the Vniuersitie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1592]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained and print show-through with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lincoln College Library (University of Oxford).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27118:1"/>
            <p>ARTICLES ECCLESIASTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CALL TO BE INQVIRED OF BY THE CHVRCHWARDENS AND THE SWORNE-MEN WITHIN THE Dioces of Hereforde in the viſitation of the reuerend father in God, Harbart Biſhop of the ſaide Dioces: this preſent yeare M.D.LXXXXII. and in the XXXIIII. yeare of the raigne of our moſt gratious ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lady Queene Elizabeth, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And ſo hereafter till the next viſitation, &amp; from time to time to bee preſented.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at Oxford, by Ioſeph Barnes Printer to the Vniuerſitie.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:27118:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27118:2"/>
            <head>ARTICLES TO BE INQVIRED OF, IN the Dioces of Hereforde.</head>
            <p>FIrſt ye ſhal enquire &amp; truely preſent vpon your oathes take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whether you doe know of any, which hath thruſt himſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any funccion Eccleſiaſtical without ordinary calling, as, to ſay publike ſeruice in church, or chappel, not being lawfully or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Deacon at the leaſt?</p>
            <p n="2">2 Whether your Parſon or Vicar be knowen, ſuſpected or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to haue bought his benefice, or come to it by any ſimonicall compace made either by himſelfe, or others, directly, or indirectly: or do let out his liuing, or any part thereof to any, in conſideration that he hath obtained the ſame:</p>
            <p n="3">3 Whether your Parſon, or Vicar, Curate, or miniſter, or any other Prieſt or laiman or woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do wilfully maintaine or defend anie hereſies, falſe opinions, or popiſh errors, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the lawes of almighty God, and true doctrine, by publike authority now ſet foorth in this realme, and what be their names?</p>
            <p n="4">4 Whether your Parſon, Vicar, or Curat, doe not ſay commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> praier in your Church, or Chappel, diſtinctly, and reuerently, and in ſuch order as is ſet forth by the Lawes of this Realme without any kinde of alteration, and at du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>d conuenient howers? And whether your Miniſter doe not ſo turne himſelfe &amp; ſtande in ſuch place of your Church, or Chancell, as the people may beſt heare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſue? And whether the holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts be not likewiſe miniſtred, reuerently in ſuch maner, as by the Lawes of this Realme is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and whether vpon wedneſdaies and Frydaies not being holy daies the Letany and other praiers appointed for the daie bee not ſaid accordingly?</p>
            <p n="5">5 Whether your Miniſter or any other not being licenced take vpon him to expounde ſcripture, &amp; thereby omit vpon any ſunday the reading of a part of an Homily, at the leaſt, or vppon any other occaſion doe omit the ſame?</p>
            <p n="6">6 Whether your Miniſter doe not read the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mination againſt
<pb facs="tcp:27118:3"/>
ſinners, with certaine praiers appointed, at the leaſt thriſe a yeere beſides the lent time: and whether he doth not reade the Queenes Maieſties iniunctions quarterly in the church?</p>
            <p n="7">7 Whether he haue preached or cauſed to bee preached his monthly or quarterly ſermons at the leaſt, and who they bee that preached them, and whether he haue ſuffered any not licenced to preach, or forbidden any that was licenced, and whether hee, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other, haue preached, declared, or ſpoken any thing in deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the book of common praier, which is ſet forth by the lawes of this realm, diſprayſing the ſame, or any thing therin conteined.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Whether any open notorious fornicatour, adulterer, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil liuer, by whom the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation is offended, haue without due penance firſt done, been by your Miniſter admitted to the holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, or any malitious perſon, that is notoriouſly knowen to be out of charitie, or that hath done any open wrong to his neighbour by word, or deede, without due reconciliation firſt made to the par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty, that is wronged: or any that at the time ſtood excommunicate, or a ſtranger of another pariſh?</p>
            <p n="9">9 Whether, your Parſon, Vicar, or Curat, haue admitted to the holy communion any of his pariſh being aboue twenty yeares of age, either mankinde or womankinde, that cannot ſay by heart the ten commaundements, the articles of the faith, and the Lords praier in engliſh, and what be the names of thoſe, that cannot ſaie the ſame, or being aboue foureteene yeares and vnder twenty that coulde not ſay the catechiſme allowed and ſet foorth in the booke of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon praier. And whether your miniſter at times conuenient before he adminiſter vnto them, and namely before Eaſter yeare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe vſe to examine his pariſhioners, whether they can ſay by hare the ſame, which is required in this behalfe. And whether hee marry any perſons that were ſingle before, that cannot ſay the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaide catechiſme?</p>
            <p n="10">10 Whether your Miniſter on euery ſunday and holidaie in the after noone before euening praier do cal for, heare, &amp; inſtruct, al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> youth within your pariſh of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, age of both ſexes in the
<pb facs="tcp:27118:3"/>
catechiſme, or at the leaſt ſo many of them by courſe, as time will ſerue, and as he may wel heare and inſtruct for halfe an hower at the leaſt, before euening praier in the tenne commandementes the Articles of the beliefe, and the Lordes praier, and diligently exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and teach them the catechiſme, as it is now allowed and ſet forth? And whether for that purpoſe he doth take the names of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all, and by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ourſe cal certaine of them by name euery ſundaie and holiday to come to the teaching of the ſame, and preſent to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary ſuch quarterly as refuſe to come to be catechiſed, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he doe diligently viſite the ſicke and comfort them with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to contribute by wil for the reliefe of the poore, as their abilitie ſhal ſerue?</p>
            <p n="11">11 Whether he be diligent in ſtudy of the holy ſcriptures for further increaſe in knowledge and for that purpoſe (if he be vnder the degree of a Maſter of art) hath of his owne at the leaſt, the new teſtament in latine, and Engliſh, and whether he doeth dailie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre certaine chapters thereof togither, and obſerue ſuch orders, as for his increaſe in knowledge, are ſet downe by his ordinary, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing at vacant times ſuch good &amp; ſeemely exerciſes as may keepe him from ſluggiſhnes and idlenes?</p>
            <p n="12">12 Whether any Miniſter haue maried any in times forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the Eccleſiaſtical Laws, or without banes thriſe asked, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the ordinary, or hath vſed the forme of tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing, for woman after childebirth, being vnlawfully begotten with childe otherwiſe then in a form of a penitent perſon <hi>viz.</hi> in a white ſheete or other habit preſcribed by the ordinary, or vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other day than a Sunday, or holyday: or before ſufficient cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion taken, that ſhe ſhould not depart the Pariſh, til ſhe ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme ſuch penance, as ſhould be enioined by the ordinary.</p>
            <p n="13">13 Whether your Miniſter vſe any other Rite, or Ceremony in the Church, than is preſcribed by the booke of common praier, &amp; whether he or any other, keepe, or vſe any ſecret Conuenticles, Preachings, lectures, or Reading contrary to the Law, and what be their names?</p>
            <p n="14">
               <pb facs="tcp:27118:4"/>14 Whether your Parſon, or Vicar, doth not in his own perſon at the leaſt, ſometimes in the year, both ſay publike praiers him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and alſo adminiſter the holy communion, according to the booke of common Praier?</p>
            <p n="15">15 Whether for the retayning of the perambulation of the cir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuit of your pariſh the Parſon, Vicar or Curat, churchwardens &amp; certaine of the ſubſtantial men of the pariſh in the daies of Roga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, commonly called the gange daies, walke the accuſtomes boundes of your Pariſh, and whether in the ſame perambulation and going about, the Miniſter doe vſe anie other rite, or ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, then to ſay or ſing in Engliſh the one hundred and three and one hundred and foure Pſalmes, and ſuch ſentences of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as are appointed by the Queenes Maieſties Iniunctions with the Letany, and ſuffrages following the ſame, and reading of one homilie alreadie diuiſed and ſet forth for that purpoſe, with out wearing any ſurpleſſes carying of banners, or handbels, or ſtaying at Croſſes, or any ſuch like popiſh ceremonies?</p>
            <p n="16">16 Whether any doe ſerue as a Miniſter, or Deacon not li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenced vnder the Ordinaries ſeale, or ſerue two cures, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any Miniſter comming out of another Dioces, hath not the Ordinaries letters teſtimonial concerning aſwel the cauſe of his departure as his behavior, and what ſtipend your Curate hath by year?</p>
            <p n="17">17 Whether is your Miniſter a peace maker and exhorter of his pariſhioners to obedience toward their Prince, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that be in authoritie, and to charitie, and mutuall loue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelues, and ſuch a one as is no ſower of diſcord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt neighbours?</p>
            <p n="18">18 Whether your Parſon or Vicar, ſuffer his buildinges or Chaunſell to fall to ruine or decay, and whether hee or any other haue taken awaie, or diſcouered any Church. Chappel, or Chauncel, or any part of them: any church-porch, veſtrie, ſpittle, almes-houſe, or ſuch like, or hath pulled
<pb facs="tcp:27118:4"/>
downe the belles, or hath made anie ſpoile or waſt vpon his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, either in his timber, or woodes, or by felling trees in the church-yearde?</p>
            <p n="19">19 Whether the Miniſter and church-wardens (according to her Maieſties Iniunctions) doe keepe well the Regiſter booke, and therein regiſter al weddings, buryings, and Chriſtnings, and once every yeare exhibite a copy thereof by Indenture to the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Ordinaries Regiſter and if it haue not beene done, which of them it was long of?</p>
            <p n="20">20. Whether your miniſter hath executed and publiſhed all ſuch proceſſes and other thinges as hath from time to time ſince the laſt viſitation beene ſent vnto him from the ordinarie. And whether he hath made any certificates of penaunce orderlie and penetently done, which hath indeede beene ſcoffingly, or impenitently performed or done at other times, or in other ſorte then was preſcribed by the Ordinarie, or elſe not done at all?</p>
            <p n="21">21 Whether your Parſon, or Vicar hath at any time ſince the thirteenth year of the Queenes Maieſties raine, made any manner of leaſe, or graunt, of his Parſonage, or Vicarage, or any part thereof (he being abſent, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> reſident vpon the ſame) to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other, then to his curate, that did or doeth ſerue his cure, in his abſence?</p>
            <p n="22">22 Whether hath your Parſon or Vicar mo benefices then one, how many, and in what countries be they, and what bee the names of them, and whether is he abſent from among you aboue eighty daies in any one yeare in al, not being lawfully qualified &amp; diſpenſed withal, &amp; being ſo licenced, whether is the Cure ſerued by an honeſt learned Curate, whether doth he not at the leaſt for one month in the year, keepe hoſpitality at his liuing, &amp; alſo giue, if his benefice be aboue twenty pounds a yeare, the fortith part thereof to the Poore?</p>
            <p n="23">
               <pb facs="tcp:27118:5"/>23 Whether any Miniſter doe forſake his function and giue himſelfe to any other trade of life, then is fite, or may be incident with that calling?</p>
            <p n="24">24 Whether doth your Miniſter keepe any ſuſpected woman in his houſe (or being not maried) any woman not of neere kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto him, or doth he liue in any tauerne, or alehouſe, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly reſort thither, or is he a hawker, or hunter, or a gameſter, at any game or other then at ſhooting, or otherwiſe ſuſpected of any notorious crime, or any euill example of life?</p>
            <p n="25">25 Whether doth your Miniſter keepe, or ſuffer to be kept any Alehouſe Tauerne, or Victualing houſe in his Perſonage or vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carage houſe?</p>
            <p n="26">26 Whether doth your Miniſter vſe any exceſſiue, or vnſeeme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kinde of apparell not commendable in that calling?</p>
            <p n="27">27 Whether the Patrone haue freely beſtowed the benefice without any Simony, directly, or indirectly, betweene him and the incumbent, or any other?</p>
            <p n="28">28 Whether your Scholmaſter teaching within your pariſh openly, or within any noble or gentlemans houſe, or in any other place there be licenſed there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by the ordinary? Whether, doth he teach ſuch bookes, as be commaunded to be taught, and that diligently? And whether is he reputed of ſincere Religion, and honeſt conuerſation, and frequenteth diuine ſeruice or no?</p>
            <p n="29">29 Whether haue you in your Pariſh Church, or Chappell the booke of common Praier, with the newe Kalle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, two Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, the great Engliſh Bible, the two Volumes of Homilies, the Paraphraſe of Eraſmus in Engliſh, the Table of the Ten com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements, whole, and vntorne, the Table of degrees of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanguinity, and Affinity, a conuenient Pulpit, a decent Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion Table on a frame, a Linnen Cloth to couer the ſame, with ſome other couering of ſilke or ſuch like, a Communion Cuppe, &amp; a couer of Siluer, a decent Surples with ſleeues, a ſure Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with two lockes for the Regiſter booke, a ſtrong Cheſt for
<pb facs="tcp:27118:5"/>
the Almes Boxe, with three lockes thereunto, &amp; all other things neceſſary to the Premiſſes?</p>
            <p n="30">30 Whether doth your Parſon, Vicar, Curate, or Miniſter weare any Cope in your Pariſh Church or Chappell, or miniſter the holy Communion in any Chalice heretofore vſed at Maſſe, or in any prophane Cup or Glaſſe, or in any other kinde of liquor, then wine?</p>
            <p n="31">31 Whether are all Altars taken downe, to the very foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the place whited, and paued vnderneath, and the Roode-lofte downe to the Croſ beame, all ſuperſtitious bookes vſed ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Church, or otherwiſe defaced, togither withall monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Superſtition and Idolatry, as Veſtiments, &amp;c. And if not, in whoſe cuſtody are they, or any of them?</p>
            <p n="32">32 Whether any Church-wardens ſince the laſt viſitation haue ſuffered any vnmaried woman begotten with childe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part their Pariſh before ſuch pennance done as was enioyned.</p>
            <p n="33">33 Whether is your Church, or chappell, and chauncell ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently repaired, and churchyard decently and ſufficiently fenced and kept cleane: if not, in whoſe default?</p>
            <p n="34">34 Whether haue your churchwardens from time to time truly leuied xii. pence for euery day, of thoſe who abſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues from church, and whether hath the ſame beene beſtowed vpon the poore as it ought, or no: And whether the churchwardens them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues haue abſented themſelues, or beene negligent in their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or in frequenting diuine ſeruice, and whether doth you Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>moniſh the churchwardens, openly in the church after the ſecond leſſon at morning &amp; euening praier to looke to their charge in this behalfe?</p>
            <p n="35">35 Whether haue any of your churchwardens or ſwornemen, ſince the laſt viſitation, or at that time, concealed any diſorder or crime done in your pariſh, or not preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted the ſame to be reformd?</p>
            <p n="36">36 Whether any of your churchwardens without iuſt cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:27118:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
haue or doe delay, to giue account euery yeare of the church goods and rentes, and whether they or any of them detaine any of the churchgoods or common ſtocke in their owne handes? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the ſtocke of the poore mans bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e faithfully, &amp; indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſtributed to the poore without any partiall affection?</p>
            <p n="37">37 Whether any churchwardens, haue continued in that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, at any time, aboue one yeare without a new election?</p>
            <p n="38">38 Whether the clarke be appointed, according to the cuſtome of your Pariſh, whether is bee obedient to the miniſter in ſuch thinges, as belong to his office and vſeth diligence in keeping all ſuch things, as belong to his charge, decent and cleane; whether is he able to read diſtinctly, and to anſwere as appertaineth to him in the church, and whether is he ſuffered to read any thing in the church, ſaue the firſt leſſon and the epiſtle?</p>
            <p n="39">39 Whether when any man or woman is paſſing out of this life, the bell be touled to moue the people to pray for the ſicke per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and whether there be any ringing for any that died out of the Pariſh, and whether for any dying within the pariſh there be any more ringing than one ſhort peale before, &amp; another after the buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al: and whether on Alſouls euen or day, or any Saints euen, or on any abrogate holidaies, ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> any other ringing then is vſuall on common working daies, or other th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n ringing to common, praier, or ſermons, and that but moderate: &amp; whether there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ringing at all in time of common praier, reading of homilies, or of preaching?</p>
            <p n="40">40 Whether the miniſter and churchwardens haue ſuffered any lordes of miſrule, dancers, plaiers, or any other diſguiſed perſons to daunce, or play any vnſeemely partes in the church or church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yarde, chappell or chappel-yarde, if they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> what be the names of ſuch lordes of miſrule, dauncers plaiers &amp;c. And whether are there any plaies or any drinkings kept in any of the ſaid places, who maintaine and accompany ſuch?</p>
            <p n="41">41 Whether any excommunicat perſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> intrude himſelfe to diuine ſeruice or the Sacrament, &amp; who are encoragers and kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of company with ſuch as remaine excommunicate?</p>
            <p n="42">
               <pb facs="tcp:27118:6"/>42 Whether any holy daies, or Fiſhdaies abrogated by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, are either by your miniſter bidden, or by any other obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſuperſtitiouſly, or any feſtiuall daies vſed a new by any with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out lawfull authority?</p>
            <p n="43">43 Whether all ſuperiours, as parents, maſters, &amp;c. doe aſmuch as in them lieth to bring to the church to bee chatechiſed on holie daies &amp; Sundaies in the afternoone before euening praier, their children, ſeruants, and apprentices both mankinde and woman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde being aboue ſeuen yeares of age, and vnder twenty, which haue not learned the catechiſme, or at the leaſt, ſuch and ſo many al them, as your Miniſter ſhall appoint to come thether for that purpoſe, and to cauſe them there diligently and obediently to heare and to bee ordered by the miniſter vntill ſuch time as they haue learned the ſame catechiſme: and what their names be that neglect ſo to doe: and who betwixt the ſaide ages cannot ſaie the catechiſme?</p>
            <p n="44">44 Whether there be any that refuſe to come to diuine ſeruice in their pariſh church or chappell, or doe not faithfully and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently endeuour themſelues, to reſort thereunto with their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and ſeruants: And whether being of conuenient age any doe not communicate orderly thrice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> at the leaſt, and namely once about Cuſtody or receiuing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ue not ſignified the ſame to the miniſter in time conuenient, that he might examine them how they were inſtructed for partaking of ſo high miſteries; and whether there be any ſtrangers, that ſoiourne in your pariſhe, eſpecially about Eaſter, and doe abſent themſelues from church, or any that be hinderers, or deriders of true religion, or of thoſe which profeſſe it?</p>
            <p n="45">45 Whether any doe praie in a tongue which they vnderſtand not, or vpon beades, or doe any way number their praiers ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiouſly?</p>
            <p n="46">46 Whether any be in your pariſh which at time of diuine prai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers, doe vſe any iangling talking, walking, or other vnſeemely behauiour in church, or churchyarde, or doe any waie diſturbe
<pb facs="tcp:27118:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
common praier, or any part of the diuine ſeruice, or doe vſe any game, or paſtime abroad at thoſe times, or ſit in the tauerne, or Alehouſe, or ſtreetes at ſuch times, or which doe worke on Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies any handicrafte worke, or which keep open any ſhoppes, for ſale of wares til euening praier be finiſhed, or which departe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore praiers be finiſhed, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth ſaie without cauſe ſufficient, or which be brawlers, or fighters in the church or churchyarde?</p>
            <p n="47">47 Whether any in your pariſh be knowen, or ſuſpected to vſe any witchcrafte, or ſorcerie, charme, inchantment, or vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful invocation, and namely, midwiues at the laboure of women, or any that reſorteth vnto ſuch for helpe and counſaile or finally blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers of the name of God, or ſwearers amonge you?</p>
            <p n="48">48 Whether any bee knowen or ſuſpected to bee adulterers, fornicators, inceſtuous perſons, bandes, or recettors of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continent perſons into their houſes, or which conuey or ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to goe away before they doe make ſatisfaction to the congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on offended, any drunkards, ribalds, malitious, contentious, and vncharitable perſon, common ſlaunderers, railers, ſcoulders, or ſowers of diſcord amongſt you?</p>
            <p n="49">49 Whether any childe being borne ſince the eighteenth yeare of the Queenes Maieſties <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> hath not bene brought to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized to your pariſh church, but hath bene baptiſed at home, or had their baptiſme deferred without iuſt cauſe, or remain yet vnbapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and whoſe children the ſame are, and whether any haue beene admitted to be godfather or godmother, which had not before that time, receiued the communion and by where they were admitted?</p>
            <p n="50">50 Whether there bee any man that hath or hath had at one time two wiues, or a woman two husbands, any maried within degrees of conſanguinity, or affinitie, by the lawes of God forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, ſo ſet out for an admonition, in a table appointed to be affired in euery pariſh church within this dioces? any diuorced keeping company ſtill togither, any married without the degrees forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, which without law haue forſaken their wiues or husbandes, or liue not togither, any maried that haue made precontractes to
<pb facs="tcp:27118:7"/>
other, any that haue made priuy contractes or maried without conſent of their parentes or gouernors, any married without banes thrice ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nly asked, or out of the pariſh church where the ſolemnization ought to haue beene, without the Ordinaries li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens vnder his ſeale?</p>
            <p n="51">51 Whether there bee any that directly, or indirectly, do take vſury, or intereſt contrary to the lawes of God, and the Realme, who they be, and what is the maner of their vſury?</p>
            <p n="52">52 Whether any ſet downe in the laſt will and teſtament, of any, as executors, doe preſume, to execute, or deale with the deads goods before the will be proued, or any preſume to adminiſter, before adminiſtration committed vnto them, any hinderers of the performance of ſuch wil, any forgers, or changers of wills, or any executors which haue not fulfilled their teſtators wil, in not pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing legacies, geuen to good and godly vſes?</p>
            <p n="53">53 Whether doe you knowe, or haue you heard of any man or woman that hath practiſed, or doth practiſe Phiſicke or ſurgery within this dioces of Hereford, not being licenſed ſo to do by the ordinary of the ſame, vnder his hand and ſeale, accordingly to the ſtatute in that caſe prouided, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> it is his, or her name which doeth or hath ſo done?</p>
            <p n="54">54 Whether your churchwardens haue ſould any your church-goods, if they haue, what be they, and to whome, and whether to the better benefit of your church or no, and howe hath the money thereof comming beene imployed?</p>
            <p n="55">55 And generally whether you know any of the Queenes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctions, broken, or any other Eccleſiaſticall matter worthy of redreſſe or no, and if you do, by the oathes that you haue taken you ſhall truely preſent it, aſwell now as hereafter, from time to time when it ſhall come to your knowledge?</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:27118:8"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="note">
            <p>
               <hi>Item that you preſent as neere as you can, the moneth, and yeare, when the faultes in the ſaide Articles mentioned were committed?</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
